I have a call this meeting, the special meeting of the House of the Council for the third day in February
20, 25.
We have not for the most important issue in the final basis, did we have problems with the streets?
Yes.
We have problems with housing, yes, we have problems with jobs, yes, not those matter if we can't
make society's issue.
But it's letting us use controls, everything that happens here, but it doesn't make it like.
So it's a very complex issue that we've all been working on for a long time and we want to
give you guys this opportunity to ask your questions to let us know what you think we should
ask.
It's going to come a time, we hope, we will not do this in future, we'll be able to
ask what we're going to ask.
Because the issue, we know that, you know, a good response is back in the mid-80s and they left
the JAR, the A-Star of Plein-Este.
They've been illegally fled this ever since.
They've had license that they haven't been invited by, but they've been a violation of license
for at least the last 20 years that they're not asking for a new.
And if we allow them, we have those new license that they're wanting to bring more feedback
operating with in the devastating the town we love.
We have to continue by, we have to dig our heels in.
All right, let's just let us know what this thing, no one's listening, no one's listening.
Nobody's talking us.
We have to do this on our own.
We'll help our law team, our tribal partners, to the city of Lyman.
We're going to fight this to the end.
We're not just going to throw up our hands and give up.
They pushed us and pushed us and tried to give us to give up.
But through mayors, through councils, through signatures, we can take you to fight.
But just go on in the mind, let's work that way.
It's home for us and if we give up now.
Then we're giving up on each of you.
We can't do that.
So do not please ask your questions.
Please give us a chance.
Please tell us your stories because they're mad.
Your stories are the lack of blood of this.
Your stories are about me containing the vibe.
My story.
I've got a flood in the first time when I was 14 years old.
I'm 50, but you're going to be 55.
So just for me, I've done a flood day for 40 years.
Nobody's coming to the county again.
They're going to be held accountable.
But I'm going to go to my grave by them.
For you guys, that's from my family.
They're going to be held accountable for what they've done to us.
And they've done it for power, money, and free.
Nothing else.
This is about free.
And we've seen this country have free all over it for years, years, years, years.
And it's got to stop.
We have to stop to the here.
We've had lots of people buy it.
We've got a max over here.
You can see what they've expanded the flood map.
They've expanded the flood map.
That's not helped us.
Let's help Jordi A.
This is trying to choke us out.
I guess with.
No.
Definitely.
I don't know.
I know.
It's what I'm putting.
So please.
Can I ask you questions?
Those are concerns.
Those we want to share this together.
And.
We'll pass this on the title.
But.
Thank you all for being here.
Sorry.
We're doing some of our journey.
Our journey is.
Or on the phone and on team.
So we have the technical difficulties.
We have to work on the side of all of that.
Text me right now.
But thank you all for being here.
I mean, this is a huge shine.
Our former mayor always said that.
You know, this was a time.
I'm very new.
The new license for GRA to, you know, fix the issues that we have.
I mean, this is our time.
So I'm going to appreciate it.
We're going to be in here.
This means I'll be a little bit different.
In the fact that we're going to have to get in some groups.
We're obviously going to do some updating.
But we're going to have some groups and talk about some different issues.
Some communities.
They talk about some of those.
So we can do.
We're going to be an asshole.
In the new license.
That would help.
I am.
So something I brought up to the.
What team is.
It's.
And it's.
Yeah, it's.
Well, it's.
It's.
So it's.
For me, my third, my third, my third, my third chair,
which is yourself as the representative you all
before the federal energy regulators
that can't apply to our licenses since 2013.
I've been involved since 2018.
So my third trip here for these town halls,
and it's already back.
We'll get to much more of the details as we get.
I'm sure that Danielle also will offer a day
that's ready to make a time for RPC office.
Yeah, here.
Can you hear me now?
Yeah, thanks.
There you go.
I'm sure that Danielle also prepared this right to me,
and I'm from RPC office.
I'm on full-time for a country that's that federal energy
where it is where everybody is.
Over at the dam.
And this is my second time in my AMA.
And I'm also deeply honored to be here
to take a minute to help me outline a solution
that it starts this community going forward.
I'm right.
Instead of council, the council, the council, we're one.
I'm council, council, council, ward two.
I'm council, council, ward three.
I'm here with Barnes, council, ward four.
I'm all in the stop to the communications manager for the city.
So after this meeting, if anybody keeps any information on flooding
or the impacts here, or you just put a get information to us,
just feel free to call me my members,
listed on the city's website.
Let's see if we were coordinating on to agenda number three.
This question.
Here's lots of procedures.
Okay, can you hear me?
Can you hear me?
Yes, okay.
Go ahead, can you go?
Okay.
I'm out there.
I'm not allowed to do that.
I'm sure it's better to do that.
I want to do that.
I'm not going to play on this.
So that's 54.
I'm just a city attorney or my AMA.
And I'm just going to talk about those speakers from the city.
But we're here for a call meeting regarding the first act.
And this will go to Mr. Wright's call.
I'm going to talk about that.
The attorney for David's writing to me are going to have things to be made.
We're going to be recording, we're going to be making for us.
I'm going to give you a message that we would like to be included in the report.
That there's normal circumstances.
This would just be a town hall meeting.
It's always being comfortable meeting.
However, because of our city.
And they are president, a member of the city business.
We have a remarkable and special meeting.
I've wanted to thank you for that.
For that reason, we've done this gathering.
I've wanted to thank you for that agenda.
It has been, hopefully, a lot of the city leaders
who have been working on this offer in our actions.
It's never the big meeting you offer in this.
And a council or other governor.
But this is the nature of this meeting.
We'll give you a quick reference of the council
to relax the figures to this council.
And then, as a brother of our attorney,
it is information that this is a relaxing thing for us.
And then, as a member of the Assembly,
it's nine in the last inch.
And then, I think, not all of us.
We have to anticipate when all of us are working out
that this is a burden for justice and the right authority.
And they concluded that this is going to be a party to have
act that a burden for visit it will be true for them
and the idea that this is going to be helpful
to relax and think for questions.
Finally, we will cross multiple answers and questions
from participants of this meeting.
And we would just ask that you're in the Q&A session.
We do that as a picture and as possible.
And we're, in fact, only one time we'd like to see if you're
trying to do three minutes or less.
I'll question, we're talking to the,
to relate to the Pintacola dance lighting issues.
And we would ask that to speak with 2,000,
and I would ask that to speak with the Pintacola dance
and I would ask that to speak with the Pintacola dance.
Thank you.
Thank you, hopefully accept this special excuse, which was a big question.
Second.
Part of...
Mark.
We discussed this issue tonight that you keep the comments respectful and honest and that maybe we're going to give this a path forward as we do with this issue that impacts us all.
Good courage for us to need it for those of all to do the right things in your name and grant anything.
I'm glad to leave you to do that on the United States of America and to do it about it.
which thanks, one nation that I got in the middle of the world would have been in Canada tomorrow.
So by exploring the work, without exaggerating, I think this is going to be the shortest
presentation of the faint of the city. However, I do have to add one element that I had to
plan on. I want to thank you for the opportunity to be here, but I also want to highlight
the importance of what the city has actually done all these years. Some of you that are
working in the past, I've shown them in where they made a policy decision because the city
did not act. It wasn't because somebody didn't do the job. The information was not out there.
And the core in GRBA made a conscious decision not to my essence because the city of
Miami was not complaining about the flooding in the 50s. They didn't realize that GRBA
was adding to that flooding, but it is so critical that you keep up the fight. You have them
on the run. You have their attention. You have the opportunity. I know it's painful, but now is the time.
So I wanted to have that come up. So as on the slide on my record, I'm going to give a very brief summary
of the state civil litigation, which is only one of the elements that's involved. This is my experience
who will take on it. The best light plans. I can move over to the point where you can find a good
person. So there's about 400 individuals in the state civil litigation. We've converted that to units
because it could be a husband and wife. It could be a corporation. It could be individuals with DBAs,
which is to give you a concept of scope. There's about 262 units who are originally involved in a community
of the city. It went into the digital husband life corporation and trust. About 300 properties.
There were many more that were flooded in the 2007 flood, but not everybody chose to be a planet.
So what we have is a situation where there are still about 139 units.
So the vast majority of people are still involved.
We've got depositions of units of about 129 units,
so a little over half, an action of them deposed.
RDA's taking the position I wanted to pose.
Every plant up in a separate room, some of them are here,
who have actually been deposed.
We have some that we have delivered the discovery to.
And yet to be deposed, we have some more
we're completing discovery.
And then there were 22 that just didn't follow through,
and didn't follow the discovery, and they've been dismissed.
Because of that, we tried to probably see the answer to the paper,
but there are a few that are full of other wayside.
There has been a ton of active, and I know you don't necessarily
have a concept of the scope of litigation, but there are about 31.
This is such a January 1, 2024.
So just basically in the last year, plus,
we've had 31 substantive findings that have been filed.
Four contested hearings, and another one's coming up on March 11,
we've had eight substantive rulings.
And I can't say we've won literally everything,
but we've won the vast majority of every contested issue.
And we do have a referees report, who is a specialist
who evaluated the natural flooding versus the damn cost flooding,
which is a significant issue here.
It is not been adopted by the court, but that's probably
forthcoming in their future.
We have ongoing depositions.
I think, yeah, we actually have something
where to post today that are in the room.
We have another spreadsheet in March.
Then we're going to take a break, but it's a break for a good reason.
This is probably the most exciting slide.
We have the status conference coming up on March 11.
We have mediation coming up.
Mediation is where there is a greater on neutral.
It comes in, meets with us, meets with GERDIA
and tries to get a resolution.
We can't do that as in the whole group.
We've done that as eight test cases.
I've encouraged every opportunity that we hear to expand that,
to try to get global or at least group discussions,
so that we're not doing a case by case, we're doing it,
and some kind of a consolidated manner.
And that's going to go on March 24th and 26th.
I'm sorry, I'm just a joke.
And the fact that GERDIA committed to three days of mediation
is significant, that's very unusual,
and shows that they are committed to having
a good discussion.
So that's all favorable.
I'm the vote.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
I'm not even saying it anymore.
Okay, so I'm devoting almost all of my professional time at this point to this case
So I'm committed I'm not letting go through what you went through and not comparing myself to you in any way
Share-to-form, but I am trying to get the thing resolved and doing everything my power to keep it moving
We there's been a time activity as I tried to hit on hopefully that substance
You don't always you don't really want to confuse activity with production, but I do think we're moving in a positive way
I think I skipped over part or we actually have test cases that are going to be scheduled in May and June in Ottawa County here
And if any of you have been involved in litigation that's when trials coming up
The things happen when they haven't been out and they kind of hold your feet to the fire console
So that that's about to occur so that that's exciting news
We will hopefully no more I July after that may June time frame
But I'm cautious about to miss GREA is a wording from the wealth funded the knowledge of all the higher good attorneys
But I really do think and I don't think I know we're on the right side of justice on this
And I've been looking at documents from the 1930s and 40s where this problem is acknowledged by science
It's just not acknowledged by GREA
So that's my short presentation. Thank you
Transition of the slides. I just want to acknowledge this is Steve, you know the baseball blight of for those of you who are listening online
I understand you may not be able to see the slides for Brazil
They will be posted online afterward and I think the situation we have only had the Facebook live
I recently do whether so that as many people's possible could listen in and I think we just had to choose between putting the slides or the video of those speakers
So just so you online now we have forgotten how to check back later the slides will be posted
Oh, yes, and
Next we're actually gonna have brief presentations from lead agency in court readiness. So if you mean the
local environmental action to men
Their local nonprofit that for many years has advocate around
Contaminationally to the target super fun site and it's impacts on a community here
So actually my slides are up, but yeah, we're gonna switch over to
feed and we have a student lawyer from the Vermont
Law School where the clinic there has been representing the agency recently
So Lauren
month was going to speak to us in the Martin line made here in town is going to speak briefly
before we go into the days right for licensing. Peace.
I'm going to go ahead.
She's new.
We're going to talk about her needed.
Yeah.
Yes.
I'm going to say all for our need.
We're all the way up in for a lot of our channels.
We're both going to be there.
We're going to be there, but we've been creating the weather.
But we're just going to ask you to get an end of the day and all the sort of
whatever you have about to waste.
We are going to be responsible after we've been calling it at the local end of our
school.
I use the orange and if it's orange we are clear and stand down with we have a couple of
capital of food apple in a product that is available to them.
As a legal permit, we've been a service candidate in the first day out of
the resources and processes that we use for those resources.
Currently, we work on a number of calls on them,
that are greater public service patients in the birth process.
These are the days when the study is uploading apps about a contingency of
a federal representative review before the entire late fall.
We've also submitted in an event release,
which is a brief file by third party on the half of the party
that we've walked in.
So, you're supporting advocacy in these ways,
you can get to the FDA at the last semester.
This semester, I was here for the last four days,
you can go public comment.
It was for first consider and number of things in their
upcoming environmental analysis of the day in the project.
Specifically, we are a candidate that first consider and
learn to accept it.
How does it do that?
We need to do that.
We're still climate change and federal representative of the FDA's plan.
So, in order for a third year, we're here on the concerns of what
population there's in this end, and we're invited to continue to work
in the federal representative of our new FDA at the very end.
That I'm just going to continue to end that.
We'll kind of get out of your mirror and let's do that.
I want to thank you for all of the meeting here and that and the meeting here.
We really appreciate it.
Thank you.
Thank you, everybody.
I know some of you, some of you, my name is Mark McLeodley.
I'm on the risk of energy and I'm over at the agency.
And I wanted to take just a couple of minutes to talk about how important it is that all people are here.
And how important it is that we collectively community have chosen to speak to use our voices to tell GRTA what we believe.
And now in this next phase we get to tell them what we want with licensing conditions which is what water and shader are going to tell us how to do great detail.
We get to ask for what we want.
What do we want our relationship with this watershed?
What do we want?
How do we want to relate to the New York River?
To talk to our creek.
How do we want to engage with these waterways that GRTA controls?
Because for a cast of power to set rules just what you try and reslicense.
Right?
I can't try to have these classes.
I have conditional my license to try the car.
GRTA is going to be given conditions on its license to operate the day.
What should those conditions be?
That's what we get to tell GRTA.
Every single idea whether you flood it or not matters.
So on these tables when we break out your license cars change starts here and it does start here.
Please take one with you.
You can propose to stay up on it.
You can send for a comment.
Every single thing you send them about what you want.
For the contamination.
For the water testing in terms of recreation.
Right?
Well, what would we like to see down in New Yorkshire River?
What would we like those banks to be public?
Right?
GRTA is responsible for all that.
We get to tell them what we want.
So thank you all for using your voice.
Thank you for coming tonight.
Please take a close car.
Please don't let out close to stay on it.
Send it for everything that one has to be read and considered.
And perhaps most importantly.
Tell your readers.
Because every single thing.
voice, so then you take these interview coming.
The rights of EAC, this is Walker and I's portion of the evening and I know Martin told you that we would be discussing licensed conditions in great detail.
My goal is actually to discuss the needs of this vision detail for me to then turn it over to you all because I feel like everyone has heard quite enough from us over the years.
Tonight, it's not about us talking at you anymore, this is about you giving us your feedback because you're the ones who live here and experience what it's like to be flooded.
We are just over-septical to take that feedback and turn it into something to file for.
So if that's that we are going to try and keep this pretty brief as to a version of slides that we presented to some folks in the community a few months ago to try and get from the initial feedback and conversation.
So for some of you this might be old hat, for those of you who are seeing these for the first time, welcome.
Welcome to the licensed condition. This is also the fun part. There you go on kind of addressing some of the past harms, Martin and the EAC team.
So some of the things they have been doing, we've also been doing quite a lot, but now I'm talking about the future and that's the fun and exciting part where we actually get to really have a voice in shaping our things look not just reacting to what the RDA has done to us thus far.
So with that we already have a brief intro about who we are.
The objectives of what we're trying to do today. Perfect.
It's to your brief overview, very briefly again of what license to even entails who is for why people keep saying that on screen.
What's going on with the licensing process for the day out where we're at in that.
And then why these license conditions or PMEs to hear people refer to them are so important and what approval is going to be.
Side note, PME is an acronym.
I mean, protection would be ancient in advance, but you also just take with them again this morning to get conditions on the license that set the rules for how to start the A has to operate the project.
I'm going to turn it over to Walker to talk about briefly some of what we've been doing this far.
Yeah, I actually before I do that, I'm going to rest the evening.
For those of you who did it to that memo, this presentation is going to be considerably shorter.
And for those of you who are interested to hear more about the legal process around damn licensing or the history of what we've done so far and where things stand.
Even deeper history to the project,
Larry gave the town hall that we presented at a couple years ago,
which was much more focused on presenting to the community,
is available online, the recording, and it has a ton of good information.
And directly, to find that video if you want to get into the weeds,
but we're going to try and just breeze through as much as possible.
Let you know some key things about bringing up licensed conditions.
And then hopefully facilitate a number of topical conversations about what those may be.
And we appreciate your patience and rolling with us with
you know, technologists and short and planning to do the weather.
And the format is a little different than we tried before and possibly a little more complicated.
And our whole fundamental is to get as many ideas from all of you
about what might go into the slices as possible.
Some things are beyond first power, we'll talk a little about that,
but fundamentally you will then need to worry about that.
It's a story of per kind and very broad powers with a list of exceptions.
And we'll worry about that.
You get as the idea is we'll sort out which ones are useful in different legal contexts.
So, well, that said, as I mentioned, we represented a city since 2013,
I represent the city since 2018, the current license for Pensacola Dam was issued in 1992.
There'll be licensing process for the dam, started in 2017.
Perk license is 130, 250 years.
So, it's a generational opportunity to change the conditions.
And flexibility to change the license conditions in the middle of a license is limited.
So, it's important to do your best when the license is in dust and run.
There's also under the existing license, there's long yellow litigation we've probably heard.
So, about right now we're through the second time before the DC circuit quarter appeals.
That's all related to the city's allegation that GIA has been violating current license by funding land,
but it's not required to profit rights to ask it to be acquired by ending for licenses.
So, that's long going to get a whole other complicated here, while we won't get into tonight, but again,
more detail in the past presentation.
So, we're in the process of other studies going on for a year, so there are still some more studies to be done.
The existing license will expire in May.
But what happens then is just for automatically is required by law to issue annual temporary licenses
essentially each year until the real licensing process is complete.
So, the May expiration.
It doesn't have a ton of impact, the annual license automatically incorporates all the same terms of the expired license.
So the process just basically works itself out that it can take a while.
As it already is.
And where we are now is GV8 file and it's final license application, a little over a year and a half ago.
The regulators have to be satisfied that they have all the information they need to go about their environmental analysis and their decision making.
And then once they reach that point satisfaction with the record, then that will trigger a 68 period where the city and lead agency and any one of you individually anybody at all can file their comments and request their license conditions with the agency.
We think that 68 period and that trigger is hard to guess.
We think it's probably unlikely to start this year.
And then how some things go.
It could be possibly a couple of three years before we reached that point.
We asked for 2018.
It has to be the Mayaa Tribe and lead agency for some specific studies in environmental contamination, for example.
And for it has yet to rule on our 2018 request for that study.
So hopefully that will happen soon.
The wheels move very slow.
In some cases in this case I can too slow from the community perspective.
Certainly.
But in case that's where we are.
But we're preparing now to put together license conditions whenever that's 16 day clock starts.
Let's see.
I think I've covered most of this.
Maybe it's been sort of implied that to make it explicit.
So you can't get the license unless it agrees with the conditions that hurt what's on.
And this is a very broad based process.
For it has authority to consider almost every different kind of interest that dams.
And every dam is different.
Every had a power project is different.
But they incorporate a whole lot of different aspects of the public interest and
certificates that are nearly all of those in setting license conditions.
Yeah.
Just to name a few, that means not just power production though.
That's one of the primary purposes of this project.
But also flood control, efficient wildlife impacts and sometimes benefits.
Irrigation that's less than an issue on this project.
Congress and navigation, water supply, recreation, environmental protection.
And many others but these are some of the specific listed in the federal power act.
So what's the stick for you all in this community?
We are going to limit the outcome of this license for generations, as I said, the new license will last 30 to 50 years and some of the effects can last much longer than that.
So the presence of the reservoir and the levels of which it's operated to give one example effect the way the sediment accumulates in the river.
And that in turn acts almost like the secondary dam in farther upstream, where the mass-moving water hits the reservoir.
The water slows down, you can imagine, seven times a fall out in a pile up dam.
So that's almost like a secondary dam that backs up the water in the water, so we're living now with those impacts from even the first license going back to 1939.
And certainly the second license, which is the current one.
And the license of process, as I said, is maybe the best opportunity to change those kinds of conditions requires this comprehensive balancing of all these interests.
And it's focused on forward-looking solutions.
Unlike though it's a very important mechanism.
It's own right what Larry does is looking back and trying to collect damages for individuals who are harmed.
The first process, you know, there's no sort of damages at the end of the real licensing.
There's not a pot of money that comes into being distributed.
So that's the way in which it's less favorable.
It's forward-looking. You could say how we present, excuse me, how we prevent potants from happening to the first place, or minimize them.
Or set the terms for how they were solved when they do happen without hopefully having a good idea.
And we're just going to skip the program.
We lost our slides.
Just a moment.
I'm going to start talking.
The next slide, they may be saying it's just a brief overview of some of the dates that have been important with the project for the last couple of years.
The slides will be available after the presentation if you're interested in that.
But, and we do have some more copies.
So that's more just a...
Again, what we're here tonight to talk about is why we need from y'all and what we're working to do to make sure that this place ends.
Incentivized, you're able to be a better citizen and a better citizen of a resource they've been entrusted to use.
Walker laid a foundation for this.
But the sort of conditions we're looking at, they can be quite broad.
We would encourage you to be creative as you're thinking about it.
what you want to task or, we're looking at not only the environment but also the way that
Dan is operated and we're also looking at batteries of administrative compliance including how
Cheeria runs their board and how they make their decisions. Those are all things that FERC has something
sure of authority over and so those are all matters you might want to look at pulling in context of
a real licensing. So we thought it might be helpful to give folks some ideas of specifically what
would be helpful to hear back on. We'll give it to even more discrete examples but this is just a
list of potential items to keep thinking. Conditions on a life in fact being again from modifications
to the way it tends operated. We have a really good example that we'll get to in a couple of slides
of what back look like particularly here. It can be infrastructure improvements not just at the
damn itself but in the surrounding areas that could be something like raising routes in my
ammo but are impacted by flooding. It can be monitoring and maintenance. It could be
an obligation for GRDA to do some sort of recording and regular meeting with the community
on but they found in what they're doing to operate better. It can be again improved communication
especially that can be important before implementing event for them to be able to plant in
no with more time for you to prepare when they know that there's something that is coming down that is
going to inherently flood the matter what they do which is always going to give a case. Even if they
operated under the best possible circumstances, there's still the potential for flooding but if
they can do their best to aid mitigate that and be communicate with that is happening, that's going to go
a long way towards where you are. There's the possibility for keeping up the recovery when flooding
does occur for them to bear some of the financial burden of doing ways to be accurate effects of that
and there's also the purchase and property rights that they need to operate the project. If there's
flooding land, that means that land is necessary for project operations and they should have some sort
of right to operate it. It doesn't have to be a simple ownership but there's those who have an easement
if they are regularly flooding down flooding lands and in many cases, this is a subject for
implementation before the ECC started thinking not currently hold those rights. So an example of project
operations that can be really helpful at the principal project is advanced raw accounts. This is
one that first are be required in a license and in multiple license but I felt this huge project was a good
example and what that would look like is GRDA to be a more proactive.
to drive down the level of the risk war in advance of severe flood events that would require a measure of pretty, you know,
studios, whether pattern monitoring and coordination with, you know, officials in the surrounding areas, but it's something that would be fairly easily implemented once you have the appropriate plan to do so.
And so, for example, in a gerda's current license, they do have some conditions that speak to this.
So, in a real licensing, what we would be looking to do is build off the existing framework, make,
make some of the risk-specific plan in place that gives, in specific detail, the steps that gerda needs to take, and what that goes like in advance of different weather events.
There's also, I know that, of course, the flooding is the issue that impacts this community, most intensely, but not all conditions have to be kind of stressful.
Thanks, or thanks, that are meant to avoid damage. They can also be things that help the dam be a better, better, better, better community, and I think, the answer ability to enjoy the weather, because it is also sort of skin recreation asset for the community.
So, in example, for that, it is enhanced recreation access, thinking about ways to make it a better resource for the community, for all the folks you use it for building and fishing.
That's definitely something that is within the balance to push forward the context of a license, and it's also a good way to hold gerda accountable for, again, making sure that they have appropriate rights for all the lands.
Because if there's land that, again, is flooded in a sense for maybe instead of that, to be a loss to flooding a access for recreation, that's something that's within the balance to discuss.
So, again, there's current license, they do have a recreation plan that requires them to look at what's going on on the way to make decisions, but we could push for something in the new license.
Like, not only does that, but also enhances opportunity and visa recreation, and also emphasizes safety and making sure that recreation opportunities are not coming at the expense of those living upstream of the reservoir.
So, I think that's what we spoke with the folks.
It's worth a little more for this meeting to start getting some initial ideas with the feedback of the community.
Again, it might be hard to be this on this slide, but this is just a few of the excellent examples about a membership community on our way to start a brainstorming.
I have a few that I appreciate.
really like our push sugar, my amount of representation of
tyrannies for and just having a seat at the table for
decision-making, seems like it would be hugely impactful,
requiring testing of flood waters to ensure, or how the better
rate of what potential toxins are in there, given the proximity to
the super fun site, raising roads in my amount of
or frequently flooded to ensure flooding doesn't impact the
first responders to get from one side of the town to the other,
and again pushing for better and more thoughtful,
pre-releases and proactive board at the rest of our
advance to severe rain events, so that that doesn't
exacerbate flooding. And that's, it's a fun time.
We're going to give you a few prompts before we start to move into our
breakout groups, and I'm also going to give
way to hear you say.
Well, I wanted to focus on because I don't like its
clearers. This license was in 1992. At that point, I had the
quarantine RDA, we're saying it was physically possible
for the feedback water effect in my hand. The city was in
the way and wrong. So when ended, it was nobody's fault,
it was because there's ignorance in the right term of the
thundabath term we just didn't know. So if you look at that license, there's
protection for great maps, there's protection for the ocean
and times. There's protection for water cloud.
There's literally nothing and no mention about strength and blood.
Because nobody did. Nobody was acting. This is the first
opportunity to have a real impact on this license.
So I go back to what I said before, now is the time. If you're ever going to put any time
that effort into it, now is the time. So brain store, be active, be energetic,
use your imagination. This is an exciting time.
Yeah, thank you, Larry. I've never really got to think that that can be
stressed enough. And we're hoping that the conversations to
many give us a great starting point for starting to coalesce my ideas
and put together what we're eventually going to file with Earth.
But you'll also see in both the slides that will be distributed after this
and through that QR code here, we have an online
there's also there on the shares too. The QR code is a
link to an online portal where if you want to send us thoughts at any time, you can.
But before you jump to that, you've got to be helpful to start talking with other
folks, the community, doing some brainstorming. And again, getting just a sense of
what human is a piano need, because that's just an acronym until it starts to become a
concrete improvement in your community. So I think at this point, we're going to transition
into the next slide.
part of the evening. Our vision for this is that we're going to set up a couple different working
groups at these tables over here. They're going to be groups by different areas of potential
coming from categories that can in these places conditions might fall into. So you can
gravitate towards the area of your interest or you can just sit wherever and start having a conversation
with the folks at the table. There's questions both on your chairs and on the tables to kind of
help you think through what conditions might be going to fall into you and how funny it is
impacted you and your family. And we'll be circulating to both help facilitate the conversation
and answering questions you might have. We'll also have Larry up here and available
the very questions particularly on the topic of either the state litigation or
raw property acquisition because that is somewhat of a murky area. We have the acknowledged
and one that definitely is repeatedly in the conversation when it comes to holding
jargy a accountable for the damages they cause. Do you have our list of kind of grace?
Yes. And folks who are online, we realize that you can't be physically in the rub with us,
but we very much want your comments and feedback to you. You can do that through the jar
code. I don't know. Is there a better way for them to engage there?
I think we can comment on things. I think that's a better way. Perfect.
Well, I think we can do drop a link for the survey and the debate book on literature as well. Yeah,
I can do the comment. Can we not be in the comments? I think we'll be back.
Yes. Our initial goal is to break out for 30 minutes.
We're going to break out for 30 minutes. We're going to talk and then we're going to encourage folks to
share their, I come back together to share any ideas or important conversations they have.
And at that point, we'll talk about that in a sense and we'll also address any additional questions that
have come up in the context of conversation. Yes. People online, we will also give you a five minute
episode that we will be back more. Sorry, I just realized we were going to
Q&A's about this process before we go to break out. But if we were going to filter,
this is an excellent question mark. Mark asks, can you explain the difference between flowage
movements and feasible ownership? And then through this, yes, we can. That's an excellent question too.
to go to the breakout session for property rights and handled there.
So, I'll run through these topics.
And we, you know, we hope to all, you know,
meet each other and discuss ideas with an topic area,
and there's signs on each of the tables over there.
If a group is too big, we've got to exercise a little.
You know, I see that just split up.
The topics we've got in mind are contamination of water quality,
tribal cultural resources, water control infrastructure,
other infrastructure, so sort of, you know,
playing impacts on everything else, you know,
the town, the city and the community, you know,
maintain infrastructure.
Community and socioeconomics in preparation
and laid access, and that would be cliche.
You know, right.
So, and we've talked about these sort of categories
of classes, conditions we might look at.
Yeah, we're really looking to you all for specifics.
So, a nice day of recreation.
If you go, oh boy, there's that spot on the edge of the lake
that used to be great, but whatever the bank is slumping
or it's never been great, but I always thought it could.
You know, at the corner of, you know,
extreme, and many eights, which is not a real place
because I can think of one that I know is on the river.
But, you know, those kind of details,
what we're looking to you for.
And the more specific we can be in asking for the easier it is
to them to say yes.
So, that being said, we were going to do a quick Q&A
to help you try, you know, if you have questions
about exactly what we're doing here, but if you've got
questions that are specific to these topic areas,
we'll try and circulate.
We have some materials, and some people will volunteer to help
facilitate some of the discussions.
Some different kinds of graphics for those of you who are
practically minded to sort of see some different representations
of, you know, how the backwater affects the city.
This huge one that's up here, just to describe,
and shows in yellow what's called the floodway,
which under people regulations is the area in the city
and surrounding areas where you really can't build anything
at all anymore.
Then, in the pink, is what's called,
you often hear this kind of 100-year flood time,
and so development and redevelopment
are significantly limited and often flood insurance
is required for properties that are in that area,
and then the light blue there is sort of the 500-year flood
plane, which is not restricted, but we're a very large flood,
but still, you know, in a data area.
So, I just want to example, there are smaller companies
of many of the larger graphics around.
So, I want interest you, feel free to take it with you,
or write your comments on that in a little behind.
And I think Martin mentioned the postcards,
and the agency has wonderfully over the years.
have postcards that are pre-printed with the first address and you can write your comment
and mail it. The postcards we have today are blank. So write your comment on the
Leave it here and we'll take them and harvest the license conditions that you write on.
So that's today's postcards. So with that, any other questions about what we're doing next?
As I said, it's a little bit experimental. We don't build up some patience and some openness.
The answer for more questions is, let's break out of the topic groups and talk about that's a
center question in the property register.
There's a person who has a stop and read all of them and that's that's the practice.
What is the every thing or what you say that it is worth out of the type you need to have for a work
of a. I've worked up to a 15 and we're going to want to write a letter.
I don't know if you're going to write that what we did, but not every time it's possible in there
really to write letters as we would be. So I wondered if that was something that we could consider
or if that we could have. Well, I'm going to let Shannon say she used to work for
her because it was a lawyer today, but of course she joined out for it. So she knows exactly how
how these comments can incorporate it. I think that's an activity for another day, but yes,
about it will do. Yeah, I can introduce that quickly because we have how the community
would be right letters that passed. I think that's been tremendously effective to show for
how invested folks are and also to explain the extent of the impact. We can absolutely keep doing that.
And we're happy to discuss some sort of forum for us to help folks do that and feel more comfortable doing it.
I put that in a separate bucket from what we're trying to accomplish here because what we are trying to put together here
I think will be most effective to be presented to work as a single cohesive piled filing that provides
all of our ideas in one place. I think that's the best in both in terms of these lessons in
decisions that the city is going to put forth.
At the same time, your individual's stories
from making tremendous valuable and important.
We would encourage you to continue to share this with Firk.
I think those two things are separate tracks that go towards
our ultimate goal, but I think this particular layer
after it is best accomplished by us putting something
together and filing it as a single organized piece,
rather than having Firk get a bunch of letters
with different conditions on it.
I think that's the best way to make sure they really engage
within and have it presented to them
in a way that's going to give them a distraction.
Is that a two-year question?
I think, though, in that case, I think it would get you out of five
of this to see how I've been, well, the path to facilitate that
is not to take your involved in the kind of way
from that, the field is not to take awful.
Absolutely.
I've got any more questions.
Thank you.
I think it was time to library, not to people
in writing letters, in a time to try to do it all.
Thank you.
Thank you for helping me with that.
Yeah, that's excellent suggestion.
The library has some potential resources for writing letters
for submissions.
No, there we have a few of these.
Excellent.
Thank you so much for your T-Shade.
Yeah.
All right.
Any additional questions or?
I'd like to say that that must be right.
And I agree with 100%, because everybody
is always different.
My story is different.
They'll apprehend us.
Your path was not soft.
Get medical attention, they're not blood.
The fact is that they're different.
The fact is that the rest is my turn.
There's no effect.
The house is seeking healing and work.
Your name is a real person.
The fact is that it's striking.
So in the other part of the room,
I'll see the different faces, the gym, the system.
It devastates the sense that there's such a business down.
That's their livelihood.
So the fact is that everybody is different.
So I can tell you your story.
But any part of your story can be impaired from you,
because the fact is that each one of you
are different than those of you.
Then we all hit us deeper.
In three, four years, there's a long time to applescars
that people understand as far as they leave.
Watch if my parents struggle to fix the house
and to try to prepare it and live in a camper
or a driveway for months, on my dad, and try
to achieve their optimization.
And this is all different.
It's as far as I'm different, but I think
for it is to hear those.
They need to see those for us.
But they won't see it for me, they got to see it for me.
I don't want to reframe this a little bit, if you're set in there, play a kid, you don't want to make this situation better.
That's what we want to hear.
Everyone that said, I think there are signs that look like this on each of the tables.
So if you got a place you want to start, you know, go find your people in that group and we'll get a half hour.
So 730, a little reconvening, and have a report back, so we don't have to do it formally, but anybody who sort of has an idea that came out of your discussion will ask me if you're comfortable with sharing.
That's the mic.
We'll be open to you on any of that.
I don't think it relies on somebody in the end.
And if you have to go take that QR code with you, use that link to submit your comments online.
Share with your friends and family.
Thank you all for that.
We'll see you around the tables.
Yes.
All right, folks.
Thanks for coming with us on this journey.
It seems like folks had some really good conversations.
We appreciate everyone engaging.
We're going to transition now to abortion.
We're going to transition now to abortion, where folks didn't share some of what they talked about.
Again, we know that this is a lot to ask folks on a Thursday night.
It is Thursday night.
Great.
I've done a short, weird, cold week.
We're going to get a play on Thursday night.
So again, we'll reiterate that if you do need to run, please take that QR code, keep giving us that feedback.
But if you're able to stick around, we'd love to hear from you.
I think we're going to try to keep this somewhat discreet.
But we do want to hear as much feedback as people want to share.
So if there is anything that came up in our group, that you particularly want to make sure other folks are aware of everything.
It was a really great idea.
This is the time.
And if you raise your hand, I will personally come and bring you this microphone.
Everybody's got any quarters.
Can't.
I'm going to do it.
Sorry.
Can you say those two shans?
I'm going to do it.
So basically we basically have a brief discussion and we focus primarily on the economic development and the impact of flooding on the economic development.
And one of the things that I think needs to be considered is we know that in plus talk about this at the beginning,
and later that it comes down to one thing and one thing only, that's money.
GRDA generates a lot of money by flooding my amount.
And any of us, they sell any property they buy, it's pennies on the dollar, compared to the money that they generate off over one flood.
In my thought process, basically says we need to establish an economic development disaster recovery fund.
And to fund that mechanism, we need a set of percentage that would affect all the profits generated by GRDA during the time period we flood.
And the reason that's important is because every time we flood our businesses have to shut down, they don't get to generate revenue.
That affects their livelihood, their profitability.
It affects their ability to pay their employees, it affects their ability to feed their children and pay their own mortgages, whatever the case may be.
On the other side of that, it also directly impacts the city of Miami in the loss of sales tax.
And so I just feel like we can establish some kind of rate based on during the flood state when we're flooding, every time they get up on a certain level.
But they have to pay an extra percentage of all profits generated during that time period.
Into this recovery fund, could be monitored or managed by the city of Miami.
My organization can certainly help with that.
But it's to direct purposes to do two things, just to help those businesses survive to get them over the hump of the loss of business operations.
And number two, to keep the city afloat, because sales tax is huge for the operation of the city.
If we want better streets, if we want better police and fire protection, we have to have a mechanism to recruit those losses.
And so I just would say that if there was a way to look at that, we cooperate them into the ass or the wants for that.
I think that's very dual.
Just to spend on that, we need to use that fund to relocate some of those businesses.
Because GRDA is not going to be an interest in businesses and reopening in spots that have had those troubles.
So we can have that come on to it. I think it might be more palatable than that.
I just feel the correct one.
I don't want this.
I don't want this. I really want to kick this off.
Sorry.
I think we're all right.
Okay.
All right.
I'm Mark Osport.
The Hayes and Quinn.
That's so funny.
No, I think we're brothers a long time.
And I think there's some very basic things that we need to start with.
And then I think there's an ask list.
All right.
The first thing is, and they alluded to it earlier,
is to make GRDA be in compliance with its previous license.
Because what that does for us is it makes them by the easiness
adequate to operate the day in which it is somewhere at 13 past 8 years.
What happened to our community?
Give me this just a second.
In 1986, we had good close.
And then we had a huge fun.
And my dad and Chuck Goldenberg and a few people with the banks.
They hired a search server for Fortune 500 companies to come and help replace the plan.
The week the guy came.
What's the week at the age of six?
And they met him out.
And the old hotel out there.
Next to the Turkpike.
And he said, you guys don't even bother hiring me.
As long as you have this problem, there's nothing you're going to ever do.
You can make a street in the country.
And since that time, we have been labeled.
You know, the state of the public community.
And we really aren't.
All right.
What we need to be told to start with is not only to people
to be, you know, be made whole in terms of their properties.
But we need access.
We need a bypass that connects I-44 to 125.
We need the connect highway can going out west.
So that the hospital doesn't have to stay in ambulance.
There's a big city in that station.
Fire trucks on the other side of the roof.
After those things, our community will be really different.
Right?
It would be really different.
We need that map.
Those colors include a lot of houses where people still live in.
In the past and maybe wrong with this.
I think the city has had 400 abandoned properties.
It's time for the email.
I was a little bit of a trap.
I've heard that in the right area in our community.
But anyway, the city didn't have to care those down.
And they've maintained those properties.
And they've done it for.
Well, I think here it is, you can be able to count it for that.
I think we can crack this cost, and this cost can be given back to the city.
There are a lot of other things that we can do that made our community better, but this is really where hope stops.
It's going to change this, and that's okay, because it's the only way we can go forward and not be stigmatized as a flag community.
The rebuilding is going to be painful for some people.
But it's going to be our chance to really have hope.
There are a lot of things that are specific that we may want to ask for.
For instance, how do we protect any of them, which is a great institution for us.
And, you know, do we do with dikes?
You can't really locate the whole thing.
I mean, either there are lots of questions like that, that's the softball field.
We get a softball complex, and now it's let's all in time.
So, after you get through the big stuff, the rest of it is things that we put in this to ask for.
So, those are the ideas we need.
If you have some idea that seems silly, well, is this going to make you silly?
So, go ahead and stand up and say something.
So, thank you so much.
There really are no silly, I guess.
Sure, correct.
Better thought.
My group, we were talking about warballing, tendons, and conversations was finding ways for G or E A to be good to steward.
A warballing, a warballing throughout their watershed.
But in this last time, they held a public event in my mouth.
When this last time, they came up here and really said,
hey, we want to talk to people about war issues up here.
Right?
So, how we try to correct this, not it?
How we try to correct this, not it?
Well, one thought is for G or E A to be required to monitor for things like algae and metals are not quite good.
Since we know a lot of testing is going on.
We know that tribes are tracking these things.
But G or E A needs to have some skin.
They need to have some campbell because they are flood wars spread this up over our homes.
When they flood us, this is what they need behind.
So, if they can be assisting actively engaged with E A with DQ.
anyone else that tried to grow a gauge in this testing of water quality. They need to be
part of it and they need to be reporting it back to the public at public events. They need to be
better advocate for the protection of water. Remember all that you read out to a few years ago?
Right? There's just terribly dangerous photos. They need to be proactive about that. They need to
be telling us not just people who live at the rate, they need to take their upstream response
totally seriously. So anything that we can do to get that monitoring, testing, communicating with
the public. Opening gates early also has environmental consequences. If it reduces the amount of
time that water stands on people's yards, that's less time for lead and cadmium and zinc to settle
into ground and soil that we may have already had for lead, clean them up to make them safe for our kids
to play. Right? They should be holding public events here. They should be encouraging
what they're testing, done by the health department. Right? All these things to improve our community health.
And I've had some great ideas about how to encourage them to be better stewards in these specific
ways. I have some others that I can share as well as later.
We should see if they can be able to share it in the end for what I feel we can do.
Oh no, I don't know. I don't know if I can do that.
But thank you so much, I think. I'm already very good breath of different kind of categories. There's
the environmental issues. There's the health issues, there's just the devastating
generation on the impact on the community. So that's the point of that's to kind of get those thinking
about these different areas and organizing your thoughts. Any rounds?
Thank you so much. If we don't have a specific more suggestions of license,
could you suppose to want to share it? We did play to have a broader Q&A on these related to
licensing enforcement. So this issue is there are various property rights that can be acquired by
environmental entity through a condemnation. One fee simple is they literally buy a problem and then
the other option that's been referenced many times here are easements, flowage easements. They actually
have different kinds of easements already purchased.
these, but this is just temporary storage, these, but this is the next layer. That's where they have the ability to just let the water sit on the property,
which is then would be cost more. The more it writes, the more restrictions the more you have to make for an easement.
Jerry A went through a period where they wanted to buy property, and then they realized when you buy the property, then you're responsible for maintaining the property.
And so that's become less favorable. So, this goes all the way back to the studies in the 1930s and 1940s, and I'm not going to go definitely into it, so they don't glaze over on me.
But they should have bought the elevations in the 70, just using row round numbers. They bought to 70, 60, they said they didn't have the money to be able to buy to 70.
That's where they had all these ongoing discussions in the 50s and 60s. That's where in the 60s, they said nobody up here is granted about all the funding that's happening in 51, so we're not going to buy these ones.
We're just going to defend lawsuits, but that again is one of these analogies, one of these issues factors that goes into buying easements.
They actually have the 11 different types of easements that they purchased over time. They didn't apply the restrictions that are included in some of the easements.
You should not be building the structures on it through the technologies, and you shouldn't be expanding structures.
They can the concept of employers floating over this property, anything that would increase the resistance direction to a third city can do it.
So, some people don't want that I think the point of why we're having this discussion is that everybody wants the easement on their property.
GRDA can through combination for private property and that's through a combination action and there's all process of how that's happening.
They can negotiate with the landowner to see if there's a willingness to agree on a price and if not, they go through the vacation and go to the three of what they call commissioners.
So, it's complicated process, and don't just think, oh, we want easements. It's a more complicated analysis than that.
And really, if there is an easement that's on the property, it's significant the devaluess problem and it's significant the elements that are used to that problem.
So, it's not something to just have a nature of reaction to everyone.
It's going to be fairly, I'm screwed, they have some thought in what they want to go with these ones.
My other side of that that I've said many is they're treating like they have authorities in it.
So, you have the negative already and they haven't paid you the value for it.
So, yes.
and it was told that it was a little bloody moth.
He was needs much with it, not a gentleman,
but he had a strike.
Sure.
I've been having this bite.
I've been looking for you, man.
Well, if it's good, if your property's both 760,
there isn't a flow of cheese.
You know how they...
The highest they bought to 760.
I know at that time, the chitting junior said,
I was the only one to have it.
He said, could be moved by that carap.
Because it was moved by that carap.
I don't see this much.
Just raise that carap.
How did it get?
Well, I think that one place where there's a disconnect
is the flood maps are part of a female process
that's designed to just figure out
the likelihood of a given disparity or depth of the flood.
Because that female flood map in process
doesn't directly connect into the causes of the flood.
So if there is, it's not just an act of God,
there's an entity that's out there causing some of that flooding,
then it fled through that easement.
You've got to claim for damages, you know,
that are violating their fertilizers.
Right?
There's a bunch of consequences, you can flow from that,
but not necessarily automatically.
And so that's where disengagement on multiple fronts is so important.
So there's massive properties here in my house,
that are with that flood plan.
Then don't have these things.
Yeah.
Medivin, then.
Right, it's mine.
I've raised my level for the next 12 inches above,
who said, could it have?
You see, you can hear it came out differently,
or that put it more on a telephone pole right there
than the other man.
I raised it higher.
And it's a needy board.
What any mistakes that have to look?
Right.
What markers point is just because there were kind of floods
zone, it's not named.
There has to be any reason.
Maybe there should be.
But it doesn't have to.
It's not a one for one thing.
It's just half a ton.
And I'm just going to quickly, you know,
this one of the many maps floating around is,
is these pair.
This is a farther out, you know,
much a lot of what county.
This one is close around on downtown.
It's different than what you're holding.
But this one shifts.
This is actually from the complaint that our firm filed
with fur in 2018, a legendary GRA didn't have enough rights
for the property in regularly floods.
And so the blue areas in these maps are roughly the area
that our best science at the time is a wall of sum.
But it's still roughly right.
The blue is the areas where we think GRA does somewhat
regularly and act of the flight,
but does not have property rights.
So, you know, if you want to look at this one,
see where your property is,
if you want to look at my property in blue.
And the blue are the back ones.
What do you want to do?
It's all in blue.
Yeah, and the one year holding is the FEMA flood mapping and that's generated quite differently
We're this came from yeah, so I'm looking at yeah, and we're gonna hang out for a journey and the channel folks want to as well
Maybe the mic so if there's folks on line still in here
I'm hearing
We were not in front of some prior to the OSM flood and that was that FEMA the term we were in
A.E. and so I had my own elevation down and it was not a E was less than that
I don't know if it's just a blanket thing is we were in the area that they all gave us all A.E
But I'm not in any war everyone has drowned me as though, but I personally played for a
Private elevation
So I don't know if that's how close or not that's
Just for the recording and for folks on line and very asked so you get cheaper flood and transparency and so it was yes
So I guess this is a bit of a mirror image of some of the problem is you know if the flood mapping is
to you know
To conservative I guess you know to pessimistic
Then you're gonna be paying all the cost of a free with what a property but really might not be so
Maybe another thing to think about is a little lines of
Help really ground through the things, you know and you do have those names regulatory bags if the facts actually aren't they back
Questions comments
Please do see me
I
And we live a block for many out our house was built in 1912 so 10 or 12
Never ever ever ever ever ever ever flooded and we have a porch that when I stand there comes up to here
And I was worried about our house getting flooded. You had this little
Plumber of the next sort and he saw me be shooting my nails. He thought it to the driveway across the street
He said are we worried that flooding your house? And I said yes, aren't you?
He said no, but you shouldn't come after the road you stand the road and look at our property. It's built up
Under our houses like this far up. He said your house ever floods this whole town
flood
Yet when Paul Markets from the lead agency camped our house and was going through it
洁 peace on a fun of our property where a flagpole is the sound flood pipe and
Paul said are we gonna get flooded insurance or like no, I mean
12 years old so it's like what the heck
So we never flooded and have your flood time now on me.
Thank you.
I do know what you mean.
Again, the technical legal term, what you all have here,
in terms of the various different overlapping legal regimes,
is a arrow.
These people, you know, flood mapping issues are serious,
and they are related.
But again, it is somewhat different than the modeling that we,
we, and Jared Ayer, are fighting over in front of her too.
So that's not to say that there are conditions that could be,
could be put in the license of round,
and it's helpful to have that reminder of how,
in some ways, much more directly impacts of that
female flood mapping.
Some of the other things that, you know,
we're doing in front of the agency.
So that's helpful.
The third way that we can have,
or the information that you can park through this time
with died almost for instance, to be taken into account
with the female flood maps, and could we ask that in the life of the license.
Again, because people are paying furniture
to never pay for insurance, right?
I'm going to throw this for our fruit expert.
It is absolutely a point that should be considered
because we have this great work that died
and Bob have done about the city.
So much data.
There's no use of the temperature tank.
Model hands, the base model of the deal is the flood map.
They use temperature tanks, model of the base.
But to your question, it does start to get into a condive,
extra-driven, jurisdictional area where
FERC cannot require female to do anything.
But we could essentially massage conditions
that influence how FERC looks at female flood planning
or how FEMA has to talk to FERC.
We could push for that sort of thing.
But the two agencies can't really force onto
do the other.
In some instances, situations, these hands in
closed main-to-tory conditions on FERC licenses,
unfortunately not in this one,
and generally never FEMA.
I think it's always a process.
But I mean, I'll just say generally,
something we all are continually trying to explain
or thinking about is, okay, FERC can't make FEMA do things.
This email can't make fun of anything, but for my people to make GRDA do things that are related
to FEMA.
So this is something that there were a couple of good comments that came out of the focus
group a few weeks ago, all of those lines about what licensed conditions could further
be paid on GRDA in response to costs that are imposed on the public through other agencies,
through FEMA costs, through, you know, ODOT paying to raise an intersection with state tax
doctors, you know, it's a generic issue.
So we're thinking about those things.
You know, broadly speaking, it takes part to help them some of you all.
So just to say that generally, I'm Larry.
I know we're running, but understand the reason the firm that the FEMA maps have been increased
is because of the increased money caused by the backwater effect.
I mean, there's a direct constant effect there.
So it's not necessarily that the science is poor.
That caused them to raise the FEMA blood claim maps.
It's directly related to the fact that GRDA is creating causing more and more backwater effect.
And so the blood claims are raised.
Yeah.
But you've paid earlier that people, they bought this type of 60, and people like gene buying good things
because they didn't feel like they weren't flipping money.
A lot of people are buying good things.
And so because of their back phase of dark knowledge,
is there somebody at home accountable?
Like a sense of honesty.
I think that's the purpose of the lawsuit that they had now will come.
It's over and over.
In Harvard.
But it is only in Harvard.
Even if we win everything.
It's only in Harvard.
There's no insult in the issue.
They're going to do it again.
And a lot of people thought that involved in the lawsuit
for paying blood insurance and everything.
I was six months ago.
I can't buy it.
Yeah.
I don't know how much they have.
It's good.
So I challenged their client.
It was $7,600 a year for blood insurance.
$7,600.
That was $1,000.
Very butter, can I?
What were you talking about?
That was my talking to you.
That was.
That is kind of a piece of bread.
I've used some bread.
Used some bread.
It's got a great question.
There's been a lot of conversations about the core of individuals.
There's been none to not.
How does it taste?
Because you mentioned here won't write it.
That's just another government agency that's now involved in this.
What part do they play in trying to help you know?
From a compliance standpoint moving forward and helping to resolve
to resolve this issue.
Yeah.
That is an excellent,
a really important question.
And I think a lot of us up here can speak about that,
that clump of the airball.
About this.
Take my baby.
So yeah, I did the court does 10 to 1.00 point at others and Jerry A was to point at the
core.
To some extent, there are just actually under the all jurisdictional issues there, and some
of those for a rule on a year ago in the complaint proceeding.
But as you might have called me, we'd won the first field of the DC circuit against
this circuit on the complaint.
You got to take back to the circuit, we heard nothing from two years, for two years after
that.
And then a year ago in January, we got back, the single best order of my career.
Just when we were getting ready to file a, you know, a first-body map to the paper, we
get this incredible order, which is not a year.
VA has a field against circuit.
But it does resolve some of the legal technical counties around the core, and that's on
the field in front of the DC circuit, which will, you know, really tie up those issues
that are directly presented with respect to the core.
So I guess the best I can give you on the details is some of the some of the legalities are
grinding through the process of being resolved.
Now, but basically the first position is that for purposes of the license, basically the
area is responsible, they have to accept the core's authority to direct the project and
flood conditions, and everything becomes of that, including, you know, the need to buy property
rice, upstream for properties, they've blood, you know, things like that.
So we're sort of finding them over the details, but some of those things are getting slowly
resolved, and so far we're going to have an interaction.
Anybody else want to add a core?
And the other thing with this all comes back to on the third front is that the gerda is the licensee.
And so they also had awareness that this specific project of what that meant with respect to the core when they
accepted their third license.
And so that means they are under an obligation to continue to be core as a get out of jail free
cart to get out of compliance from their license.
They knew that was the case.
Yeah.
They did try it.
But yes, they knew the state of the plan of the ground, and they accepted the license.
They're about that.
We now find we have a FERC, who is waiting out to holding them to comply with the license they
agreed to.
And one last thing with the letter to tell you a way more about this, but it's also worth noting
a matter of Oklahoma state law, particularly in a poor law, damages for other people.
It has been settled since 1941 that gerda is responsible for damages as a result of doing what the core tells
it.
So the Y and I will illustrate one at Oklahoma State Supreme Court case in 1941 that said essentially
what are you talking about?
So the license subject to the condition that you do with the court directs, you know, you
accept the responsibility of those actions, you know, you're responsible for those actions
because in legal effect they were your actions because you took the license.
So, anything else on the court, any further questions on the court?
I won't be saying that I wouldn't have a PN just a man out there, but let's say it on the
one of that issue again, to about a year ago, and GRDA tried to take it up on and walk
through the appeal we fought at, but they say that whatever judgments we get in this
crime litigation they're going to appeal it again on this very same exact issue that was raised
in Wyandot, the flood was 41 in the case actually was 43, and the government cool, which we
won in 2004, and now the District Court has said it again a year ago, and GRDA is saying
they're going to appeal again.
So they just will not take no for an answer to the court as to give them out of jail for a year.
I think that's a good idea to do it, and you know, part of it, how does it, hopefully that they'll
be an ultimate resolution and just an acceptance, but they've made a conscious decision that to
keep trying to mislead the situation issue is taking a can down the road and not causing the
court to be stopped by, then you mix them all in off, and then you want to do that on that road,
where they tried to take it really to that way, but I'm going to shut it.
I'm going to shut it.
That was a nice question, though.
I was just going to quickly add the big picture, I think, you know, where's that come from and
how does it, and I mean, they, you know, they're hoping, you know, beyond the legality
and all that, you know, you all, their friends, the neighbors of representers are going to stop,
you know, you know, bushels that you're going to just get worn out to tie a guy out of two
cigarettes and shut up.
So there was a, yeah.
So there's a, you know, what I'm going to do with the, the people brought out that nervous,
I'm going to came from her dispatcher, Valerie, and she brought it up, you know, she dispatches
staring at the floods, and we don't have police and fire out of the southwest part of my
ammo, and we're going to have to get on the tram bike and go all the way around, so something
to do, you know, that's not like public safety center out there in the southwest, so that
people could get, you know, I live out of the southwest because a lot of people live in the
southwest, I mean, they could get medical care out there, long course not there in a quick
time.
Something else that I heard is, it was a good, I thought it was really a good idea, you know, besides
having a member of the jury and order for the city of my ammo also.
and try to represent it, so you know, a lot of the lands they flood or you know, travel lands.
So I mean, obviously they have a big kid and that's what I think that would be a good idea.
And when you talk to them about obviously following the current license, they don't do that.
Relocation of the city facilities. There's a lot of city facilities that are in, I mean, how about, you know, page facilities that are in the floodway and floodpoint.
The obviously something they were actually relocated.
Another good idea was, first of all, additional land from GRDA as part of the relicensing.
So the city can use it to stimulate, you know, more housing.
So you know, but where that would be at, I don't know, there's different ideas.
But, you know, obviously five of these to grow.
And we can't grow up seeing areas that are going to be 100 or 500 flood lanes.
So that's, you know, helped in versus land.
Need to help mine to grow.
And then, you know, raise some flood going travel routes.
So like we said, you know, you can't be going to come in and get trucks out of mine.
I think you know, get stuck coming.
So that's a good idea.
And those people are just about to get in at this meeting.
So I'm about to happy that I didn't ask her to come in and speak.
So.
Something that's near to my heart.
And the last thing I have really is, is like it would be so nice to be getting some out of the generation business.
I mean, not so much with a dam, but I mean, just for it, you know, natural gas or something like that.
So we could not be sort of like, I don't care because I mean, we do.
To me, it's like, you know, there's students and there's two sizes of gear.
We get our power from GFA, but they also flood us.
So I mean, it's hard to be to deal with them.
And to me, so the top said they're about the public safety center.
You know, we're going to be able to those, I'm trying to get a grant that, you know, we're going to like the efficiency of energy.
You like to be sort of us to represent you.
And we shouldn't be able to apply for this.
You like to represent this.
You like to put it for the state.
And you also represent our elected for the nation.
You know, for instance, you can DC and they're not.
Senator Marshall, who is your city center right now.
I set up a face to face.
But I asked him, Senator, why are you allowing the city to flood the people that you asked about for you?
The people you're supposed to represent.
He let me get the face and said, well, later, they are very profitable cities.
That was his response.
And we just really like to thank God for those for those for those four years.
It's sick of it.
Then the person we elected, through us, right, square out of the bus, and the step-in-all, yes.
He doesn't care about the flood issues here.
He doesn't care about what you pay for flood interest.
He doesn't care.
We're going to play in the second DC, right now.
He's supposed to be represented by...
He's still a letter to the court on GRDA's behalf against all of them, but he tends to ask for our votes.
He's not standing up for us.
That's what he's likely to do.
He's not building them.
Instead of 9-1-7, and Congressal Regene, he tried to put them all spot about it.
I said, they tried to park right along.
They tried to push it.
Somebody else.
You just like GRDA passes it to the court.
The court wants to bring it back.
And GRDA, here we are, said, we know what I'm saying.
This is not our fault.
We need representation.
We're not getting it.
I know what I'm going to say to Mr. Richardson from this night one here.
But the people that are outside are going to be elected.
We're not going to the job that they're supposed to do for us.
How many times have you seen them here?
Because they don't want to face this issue.
They want to turn a violent item.
You've got any other way to the official of the state.
And they'll say, don't you want your local guy to say.
Because I don't want to take that beat.
And I don't want to give such a local guy to them.
So these elections really, really matter.
Now, of course, we're not following up.
We're not following up.
We're going to start counting.
And then two of the candidates like to be, and we're paying the price.
And probably we're sitting in a stable car room.
And there's nothing we need to know.
We got it in the middle of the board here too.
But these elections matter.
And they need to hear from us.
You know, we try to talk to centers.
U.S. centers from other states.
The first thing to ask is, well, it's part of what I'm saying.
You know, every time.
So, you know, it's the same way that sitting in an office here.
It was the exact same way.
It was part of the same spot.
And we're, we're a bad spot when it comes to that.
I don't know what we do to take it.
Except to keep fighting.
And we're going to do that for you up here.
But we need your voices.
We need you to send those letters to the park.
And we talked about it over the list.
Because that's our only hope.
This is a perfect, a perfect, a part of our torch.
And we need to carry on with the carrot force.
The mark makes it that letter to the park.
We have to carry them against us.
The way I could, their response was I couldn't know it was laughing.
So, the safety you can just send this.
You know, it kinda calls this off.
But it was the fact that he did that.
Well, we have to carry against you.
We need that, maybe, sit across the other.
You know what?
I don't know if you see me out of TV.
He's going to fight anyway.
He's going to fight things through the people around me.
You have to keep it on the fiber and keep it on the fiber, but it's not on the fiber you, and you're the one on the bone for it.
You're the one they do.
in one of the vote for, one of the vote for it, and one of the stand-up by me, and one of the stand-up by everybody else.
Let's press that.
Mayor, now they're calling it.
In just a minute, I'm ready to lay it.
Come on, round 19.
Hold up.
I'm just a second.
Okay.
I like your shirt.
Would you say a name?
Some were around 19 per hour.
How do you turn?
How are you like?
Who's that?
Very similar.
When the candidates go home, the bloodlines go around.
And you might be better off not to have Mayor, because before we argue the first time.
And at that time, I think it was final.
And they actually counted some of these as the RTA in the home of the criminal state.
And they got right at that place.
No, they don't have any.
They don't have anything to do with it.
They don't know that part or fact, but so.
And we stuck along with somebody found that case about why not that Mayor.
And then we were all in the room.
So, it's nothing new.
I have no idea how to handle it.
But they have never really cared.
It's about the money.
They're always going to take care of the link to the recreation.
And if you're trying to grow something up there, or, you know, the C, especially
all the stuff that we have in the bloodline is just, why hope would just be good, but so we can get straight back.
Because it's good, it's time.
And I wish that I had something positive to say, but it's been going on.
It's a lot longer than just looking.
So, anybody got anything positive to say?
I'm sorry.
I'm really wondering how many politicians have the nice delay points.
When we talk about the politicians as not really helping us out.
Many have ended up with a lake and a beautiful home down there.
And seeing the results of how many representatives and senators make 160,000 to 160,000 years.
There were 29 million, 80 poor million.
They got some great investments.
Anybody that's spoken, I don't want to jump in line for them or anything.
A local marketing team is a good sign.
I'm trying to keep saying, I'm rolling here.
This is a lot to be having.
Tyler, one of the things that seems clear to me, that would be beneficial for both the RDA and the city.
It's a take deal with good risk plan.
They're so good.
I only do we have the adequate infrastructure to take power there.
I put it in the grid.
But it would make...
here at D.A., we'd like to hear about the environment, and that's what people are interested in, actually.
Yeah, and I know that at one point, they had a certain amount of property, or there's the bill somewhere tonight.
But they didn't want to fight for you, sir.
Or you say anything.
Okay, another one.
I don't know if you are tolerant of that.
We actually had to say a thought about the good-rich property about the sort of the bill, so that Mark, and there is actually talks.
I guess they want to detail about how they are, but there are a lot of things I can talk about doing that right now.
Lots of questions.
I can do questions, there's a few comments, and then I've posted the links, and we'll go ahead and talk.
Thank you.
All right.
Okay, because it's up to the council.
Yeah.
It's a quick to claim around the next steps of our region and everyone.
That looks actually in charge.
So, again, this is been tremendously helpful.
It's been able to have you all here.
It's extremely helpful to hear from you, actually, what would be important to you.
And to hear how this is impacted you, individually, impacting your businesses.
In fact, if you're being amazed, that helps us do our job way better.
Because if you're not here on the graph every day, we just don't know unless you tell us.
Going forward, QR codes.
You can keep feeding us those thoughts.
Whatever as often as you want.
We will read them all.
You'll compile everything.
We will do our best to put something together.
It represents all of y'all.
Well, and all of your concerns, so that we can get.
Do our best to get for to bite on everything that you want to see in this human life.
It's for the project.
Tell your friends, so your family.
Anyone who wasn't here, shouldn't link.
Make sure they know that they can also give us that feedback.
I think also that slides will be posted.
Those have the squad-premise contact information.
You can reach out to us in each time.
Call us email us.
We'll answer your questions.
We're here for you.
And just a couple.
Last other things.
You know, tell them, you know groups are involved in.
You know, businesses, you have relationships with.
You run, coworkers, you know, churches, groups are involved in.
You know, just show that link is why things you can't fit.
But you think, you know, cares and knows a little about any little corner.
You know, there's, you know, a little corner.
puzzle. They could offer a suggestion for how to make the next license better in this one.
And you know, obviously personally, I know I speak for everybody up here, I, you know,
jumping into several conversations, each of which I really enjoyed, not at which I was able
to participate in as long as I would like. And I know there were even more conversations going on that,
you know, throughout the tables. Again, I can't stress this enough to these things.
You have good ideas or the starts of good ideas from those conversations. Make sure we get
them captured somehow on a car through the web form through telling them to one of us and email later something.
It's good to be done with those conversations and there is value in that moment, but there's a lot more value
in the relationship process that we get over the ideas. With that, you can probably head back to the city.
This is a nice one coming out. I appreciate everybody coming over here, but it's important. We serve you
this is the hottest button issue we have. We know that every day we show up, or accounts
means we know that this is on the forefront. We always got to find this value until we went it,
and we're going to win it. So we appreciate you guys coming out, give us a share of it, but don't
feel free to call us emails or our number of emails online or this whole account is here at
answering the need. It's also the same way. Actually, if I have to say that, if you need something,
you'll find the right answer for someone. But we do appreciate you coming out with appreciate your
input. Any other comment?
Thank you.
All right, that's it. I'll entertain a bunch of good terms.